Presenter: Hello, and welcome to The world of work.
Today, it’s all about working hours and productivity.
There’ve been a lot of articles in the British press recently telling us
that we’re working too many extra hours, that we should only work a four-day week,
not a five-day week, that we shouldn’t be doing eight-hour days from nine to five and so on, and,
indeed, suggesting that if we had shorter working hours, we might actually be more productive.
But how realistic is it really to suggest that people work fewer hours?
A lot of offices have fixed hours when they need to have people there,
and having fewer people in the office may simply not be an option,
not to mention that many employees may not want a drop in salary
in exchange for a shorter working week.
However, what a lot of experts appear to be suggesting is not so much working fewer hours,
but organizing your day better.
A recent study used a computer application to track employees’ work habits.
Specifically, the application measured how much time people spent on various tasks,
and compared this to their productivity levels.
In the process of measuring people’s activity,
they were surprised to discover that what was important was not how many hours people worked,
but rather, how they organized their working day.
In particular, people who were religious about taking short breaks were far more productive
than those who worked longer hours.
They discovered that the ideal work-to-break ratio was 52 minutes of work,
followed by 18 minutes of rest.
People who maintained this schedule had a unique level of focus in their work.
So basically,
what the study is proposing is that the most productive way of working an eight-hour day,
if we round up the figures from the research, is for people to break their day into hourly intervals,
followed by 15–20 minutes of rest each time.
We naturally plan what we need to accomplish by the end of the day, the week, or the month,
but we’re far more effective when we focus on what we can accomplish in an hour.
Apart from getting you into the right rhythm,
planning your day around hour-long intervals simplifies daunting tasks
by breaking them into manageable chunks.
If you want to follow the research recommendations to the letter,
you can plan your day around 52-minute intervals if you like, but an hour works just as well.
However, this strategy only works if you follow certain rules.
For example, you have to respect the hour of work – you should absolutely not be,
let’s say, checking social media, or making yourself a coffee during this hour.
Then, equally, you need to respect the break time, and ideally do something completely different,
like taking a short walk, chatting to colleagues, or reading
– something that takes you away from your work.
So now we’re going to talk to Martha,
who works in the Human Resources department of a large publishing company…
Martha: Hello.